Thomas Gray Manuscripts:
Thomas Gray Archive
- Poems, [ca. 1725]-1771; mss.poems
  - The Bard. A Pindaric Ode, 'Ruin seize thee, ruthless king!; 1757; poems.bapo
    - Bard, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0204; poems.bapo; 1 transcript of variant lines in the hand of John Mitford, partial [ll. 111-112, 114, 116] 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Transcript of variant versions of ll. 111-112, 114, and 116, in the hand of John Mitford, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, f. 85v.
    - [untitled], 17 June 1786; mss.0201; poems.bapo; 74 transcript, in form of a full score with four voices, in the hand of J. W. Callcott 230 mm x 300 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Transcript, untitled, in form of a full score with four voices, by J. W. Callcott.
    - The Bard. A Pindaric Ode, 1780[?]; mss.0221; poems.bapo; 16 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/02/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled The Bard. A Pindaric Ode (p. 47) (Ode. VI. [p. 49]). The poem, which has numbered stanzas and includes the "Argument" and the "Advertisement" as a footnote to the half-title as well as Gray's notes to ll. 5, 11, 13, 14, 35, 38, 47, 54, 57, 59, 64, 67, 71, 77, 83, 87, 89, 90, 91, 93, 99, 109, 110, 117, 121, 128, 131, 133, and additional annotations to ll. 70 ("Richard II.") and 75 ("Henry IV."), is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
    - The bard; a Pindaric ode, by...founded on a tradition current in Wales that Edward the 1st ordered all the bards that fell into his hands to be put to death, [after 1773]; mss.0275; poems.bapo; [?] transcript in the hand of John Freeman Milward Dovaston 190mm x 120mm (volume); YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 661, item R0238
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 16 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10631>
      Transcript in the hand of John Freeman Milward Dovaston, entitled The bard; a Pindaric ode, by...founded on a tradition current in Wales that Edward the 1st ordered all the bards that fell into his hands to be put to death, in his autograph Select, and Miscellaneous Poems, Scraps, Mottos &c, 1773 and later, a Commonplace book of verse by Dovaston and others.
    - Bard, 3rd August 1824; mss.0289; poems.bapo; 1 transcript (ll. 128-130) in the hand of R. Barneby; FOLG
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Dec. 2012. Folger Shakespeare Library. 15 February 2013. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=295130>
      Transcript of three lines (ll. 128-130) in the hand of R. Barneby, beginning "In buskinn'd measures move" and signed "R. Barneby Aug.t 3rd. 1824."
  - The Candidate, When sly Jemmy Twitcher had smugged up his face; [1774?] or 1777; poems.cand
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 78-79
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 243-252
    Written between January and March 1764 when Lord Sandwich's campaign for the post of High Steward at Cambridge was at its height. First(?) printed, ll. 1-32, entitled The Candidate: By Mr. Gray in [1774?] by Walpole at his Strawberry Hill Press. Published, ll. 1-32, untitled, in the London Evening Post, February 1777.
    - The Candidate. On Lord Sandwich standing for High Steward of Cambridge. By Mr Th. Gray, [1774]; mss.0026; poems.cand; 2 transcript in the hand of Horace Walpole; YALE
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 19, 80
      Lewis, W. S. et al. (eds.), Horace Walpole's Correspondence (New Haven, 1955), vol. 28, 169-170, transcript printed, with notes on both MS 26 and MS 27
      Powell, Margaret K., "Re: Fwd: Enquiry re. two MSS of a Thomas Gray poem". E-mail to the editor, 14 July 2006
      Transcript of ll. 1-32 in the hand of Horace Walpole, endorsed on the verso in Mary Berry's hand, "Gray's Verses upon Lord Sandwich, from L. Orf. 1794.".
    - The Candidate. By Mr T. Gray, [1774]; mss.0027; poems.cand; [2?] transcript in the hand of Horace Walpole; MOLI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 20, 80
      Transcript, including ll. 33-34 (crossed out), in the hand of Horace Walpole.
    - [untitled], [between 1777 and 1780]; mss.0023; poems.cand; 1 transcript in the hand of Michael Tyson; BLPL
      Zonghi, Roberta, "transcript". E-mail to the editor, 10 July 2006
      Transcript of ll. 1-32 in the hand of Michael Tyson, headed "written by Mr. Gray at the time the Earl of Sandwich was candidate for the High Stewardship of the University of Cambridge".
    - On Lord Sandwich's canvass for the high stewardship of the University of Cambridge, [1783?]; mss.0024; poems.cand; 3 transcript in an unidentified hand (32 lines); HARV
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36720>
      Transcript in an unidentified hand.
    - On Lord Sandwich's canvass for the high stewardship of the University of Cambridge, [1783?]; mss.0025; poems.cand; [?] transcript in an unidentified hand; LGLT
    - [?], [after 1777]; mss.0199; poems.cand; 2 transcript in two unidentified hands; YALE
      Transcript, beginning in one hand and ending in another, on the last leaf and continuing onto an extra leaf, in a copy of Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ).
    - The University Courtship, [between 1777 and 1826]; mss.0200; poems.cand; 2 transcript in the hand of Bertie Greatheed; YALE
      Parks, Stephen et al. (ed.), Osborn Collection First-Line Index. New Haven: Beinecke Library, Yale University, 2005, 1000, item W1301
      Ducharme, Diane, "Re: Fwd: Enquiry re. two MSS of a Thomas Gray poem". E-mail to Margaret K. Powell, forwarded to the editor, 13 July 2006
      Powell, Margaret K., "Re: apologies". E-mail to the editor, 20 July 2006
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=10646>
      Transcript of ll. 1-32 in the hand of Bertie Greatheed, annotated "Written by Mr. Gray when Lord Sandwich was a candidate for the office of Stewart, of the University of Cambridge---".
    - The University Courtship, [later eighteenth century]; mss.0241; poems.cand; 2 transcript in an unidentified hand; LELI
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=6139>
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, beginning "When sly Jemmy Twitcher had smugg'd up his face" and attributed "by Gray & not in his works", in a commonplace book, "apparently compiled by members of the Smyth family of Heath, near Wakefield, West Yorkshire" and "written c.1710 - c.1820 by six main hands here designated A-F (in this case E, later 18th cent.)".
    - Jemmy Twitcher or the Cambridge Courtship, [between 1782 and 1804]; mss.0243; poems.cand; 2 transcript in the hand of John Phillipps 193 mm x 160 mm; BDLN; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in the SCRR at the RSL, Bodleian Library, on 11/03/2010.
      Crum (ed.), First-Line Index (1969), vol. II, 1088, item W1466
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=86775>
      Transcript in the hand of John Phillipps, including ll. 33-34 (crossed out), annotated below "Written by Mr. Gray at the time of Lord Sandwichs election for High steward of Cambridge. Gents Magazine Jan. 82", and with additions "To Jemmy" before ll. 31-32 and "To Physic & Law." before ll. 33-34. In a volume of collected verse, copied from manuscripts, printed editions and newspapers, by John Phillipps of the Middle Temple and Exeter College, Oxford, 1776-1804 (Summary Catalogue, 45759).
    - By Mr Gray on Lord S's soliciting the High Stewardship of Cambridge, [undated]; mss.0252; poems.cand; 2 transcript in an unidentified hand (32 lines) c. 230 mm x 190 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/07/2010.
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 9 April 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=116159>
      Transcript in an unidentified hand (32 lines), here beginning "When sly Jemmy Twitcher had snug'd up his face", in a quarto volume of miscellaneous pieces of poetry, entitled Miscellaneous Poetry and "presented by Rev. T. Crompton", written in the 18th and 19th centuries, to which the names of the respective authors are assigned.
  - [Couplet about Birds], There pipes the woodlark, and the song-thrush there; 1814; poems.coub
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 106
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 279-280
    Composed at Cambridge in spring, presumably between 1763 and 1767, in the company of Norton Nicholls. First published in
    Mathias (ed.), Works (1814), vol. II, 596
    .
    - [untitled], November 1805; mss.0028; poems.coub; 1 transcript in the hand of Norton Nicholls; ETON
      Mitford (ed.), Works (1843), vol. v, 34
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 21, 81
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), vol. iii, 1290
      Transcript, untitled, in the hand of Norton Nicholls, in his MS Reminiscences of Gray, p. 5.
    - [untitled], May 1795; mss.0029; poems.coub; 1 transcript in the hand of Hester Lynch Thrale; HULI
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 22, 81
      Transcript in the hand of Hester Lynch Thrale, untitled, here reading "piped", in her MS Thraliana, vol. VI, 111.
  - De Principiis Cogitandi. Liber Primus. Ad Favonium., Unde Animus scire incipiat: quibus inchoet orsa; 1775; poems.lt05
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 156-167 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 321-332 (with English prose translation)
    Begun at Florence not earlier than 7 July 1740 and abandoned at Stoke Poges by June 1742. Shortly before leaving Florence, Gray sent ll. 1-53 in a letter, dated 21 April 1741, to Richard West (Favonius). First published in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), 160-167.
    - De Principiis Cogitandi. Liber Primus: Ad Favonium, 1740; mss.0031; poems.lt05; 4 autograph, revised; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 23, 81
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 22, 23, 25, 26
      Martin, Chronologie (1931), 128
      Autograph, revised, with line numbers (10, 20, etc.) and marginal notes, unfinished, annotated "Begun at Florence in 1740 ", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. I, split over four pages: p. 129 (ll. 1-27), 138 (ll. 28-79), 289 (ll. 80-151), and p. 438 (ll. 152-207). In the index to the Commonplace Book, the poem is listed as Thinking (the Principles of) a Latin Poem, unfinish'd.
    - De Principiis Cogitandi, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0030; poems.lt05; 2 transcript of variant readings in the hand of John Mitford, partial [18 lines] 180 mm x 115 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 81
      Transcript of variant readings (18 lines) in the hand of John Mitford, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. III "Mitford. Extracts from Mr Grays Common-place books", ff. 191r, 192r.
    - De Principiis Cogitandi, [between 1845 and 1856]; mss.0205; poems.lt05; 1 transcript of variant readings in the hand of John Mitford, partial [18 lines] and crossed out 180 mm x 110 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 07/10/2006.
      Transcript of variant readings (18 lines, crossed out) in the hand of John Mitford, in John Mitford, Note-Books, vol. IV, f. 86r.
  - De Principiis Cogitandi. Liber Secundus., Hactenus haud segnis Naturae arcana retexi; 1775; poems.lt06
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 168-170 (with English prose translation)
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 328, 332 (with English prose translation)
    Begun at Stoke Poges in June 1742 and sent in a letter, dated [8 February 1747], to Horace Walpole. First published, as "Liber Quartus", in Mason's Memoirs ( 1775 ), 168-169.
    - [untitled], [1747?]; mss.0032; poems.lt06; 1 autograph written in red crayon and pencil, revised, partial [34 lines], quarto
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 24, 81
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Sotheby's sale (28 August 1851), lot 53, 41, Sotheby's sale (4 August 1854), lot 230, 70
      W[right]., Catalogue (1851), [lot 53,] 9
      Catalogue of a Sotheby Parke-Bernet sale (6 April 1982), lot 53
      Bonhams sale (10 April 2013), lot 185 (with facsimile)
      An autograph of 28 lines and 6 deleted lines, revised, of Book II of De Principiis Cogitandi written in red crayon and pencil (two lines), together with a note on human desires.
    - Liber Secundus. De Principiis Cogitandi, 1742; mss.0033; poems.lt06; 1 autograph fair copy, revised, partial; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 25, 81
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 25
      Autograph fair copy, revised, here entitled Liber Secundus. De Principiis Cogitandi, unfinished, annotated "Begun at Stoke, June, 1742 ", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol I, 286.
    - [untitled], 1747; mss.0034; poems.lt06; [1?] autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 26, 81
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 131, vol. i, 264-268 (subscription required)
      Sutton (ed.), Location Register (1995), 415
      Autograph fair copy, here untitled and referred to as "the Beginning of the fourth Book" of "a large Design", in a letter to Horace Walpole, [8 February 1747].
  - [The Death of Hoel], Had I but the torrent's might; 1775; poems.deho
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 69-70
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 233-235
    Written at London in 1760 or 1761. First published, entitled Ode XI. The Death of Hoel, in Mason's Poems ( 1775 ), 58-59.
    - [untitled], [1761?]; mss.0035; poems.deho; 1 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 27, 81
      Poetic C. B., Pembroke College (1999), 30
      Autograph fair copy, untitled but headed "From Aneurin, Monarch of the Bards, extracted from the Gododin", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1070.
    - The Death of Hoel. an Ode, 1780[?]; mss.0226; poems.deho; 5 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/02/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled The Death of Hoel. an Ode (p. 99) (Ode. XI. [p. 101]). The poem, which is annotated "See Mr. Evans's Specimens, 71 and 73." on the title page, is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
  - The Descent of Odin, Uprose the King of Men with speed; 1768; poems.dooo
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 32-34
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 220-228
    Written at London in 1761, the paraphrase of the original Icelandic is based largely on a Latin translation from Bartholinus. First published in Poems ( 1768 ).
    - Ode (from the Norse-tongue) in Bartholinus, de causis contemnendae mortis. Hafniae. 1689. 4to, [1?] February 1768; mss.0036; poems.dooo; 3 autograph fair copy 324 mm x 200 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 28, 81
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=140501>
      Autograph fair copy, here entitled Ode (from the Norse-tongue) in Bartholinus, de causis contemnendae mortis. Hafniae. 1689. 4to, followed by the first line of the original poem "Upreis Odinn allda gautr &c:", including explanatory notes, used as printer's copy for Poems ( 1768 ), in MS instructions to Dodsley, sent in a letter, [1?] February 1768.
    - [untitled], 1 February 1768; mss.0037; poems.dooo; [3?] autograph 324 mm x 200 mm; PRIN
      Facsimile, showing the beginning (37 lines) of the autograph, on page six of the MS Instructions, the upper three-fourths of which are reproduced, in
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), no. 5, following p. xvii
      , where it is described
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 29, 81
      Autograph, untitled but numbered 8. and identified from the table of contents as "8. The Descent of Odin (from the Norse-tounge)", and headed "From Bartholinus, De causis contemnendae mortis. Hafniae. 1689. 4to. Upreis Odinn Allda gautr &c:", beginning "Up rose the King...", and including a note, in MS Instructions to Beattie for the 1768 Glasgow edition, originally sent in a letter, 1 February 1768.
    - [untitled], 1761; mss.0038; poems.dooo; 2 autograph fair copy; PBCC
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 30, 81
      Martin, Chronologie (1931), 147
      Autograph fair copy, here beginning "Up rose the King...", in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. III, 1069-1070. The Latin text of Vegtams Kvitha from Bartholinus is on p. 1043.
    - The Vegtams Kwitha, from Bartholinus. L.3. C.2. p.632., [before 1794]; mss.0039; poems.dooo; 4 transcript in the hand of Thomas Wharton 230 mm x 186 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 31, 81
      Transcript, in the hand of Thomas Wharton, here entitled The Vegtams Kwitha, from Bartholinus. L.3. C.2. p.632.
    - The Descent of Odin, an Ode. (from the Norse-Tongue) in Bartholinus de causis contemnendae mortis; Hafniae, 1689, Quarto, 1780[?]; mss.0224; poems.dooo; 10 transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand on Whatman paper 180 mm x 110 mm; YMAR; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in The Archives, York Minster Library & Archives, on 27/02/2007.
      Transcript in an unidentified neat and legible hand, entitled The Descent of Odin, an Ode (p. 83) (Ode. IX. [p. 85]), followed by the first line of the original poem. The poem, which includes Gray's notes to ll. 4 and 90 (with Mason's addition), is part of a section called Poems, which is separately paginated and has its own table of contents (p. 129), in a volume entitled Gray's Poems. The book carries the bookplate of Gray's friend and biographer William Mason.
  - Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard, The curfew tolls the knell of parting day; 1751; poems.elcc
    Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), 37-43
    Lonsdale (ed.), Poems (1969), 103-141
    Begun c. 1745 and completed early in June 1750 at Stoke Poges. Gray sent the poem in a letter to Horace Walpole dated 12 June 1750. First published, as An Elegy wrote in a Country Church Yard and printed by Dodsley, in 1751.
    - Stanza's wrote in a Country Church-Yard, [1749?]; mss.0043; poems.elcc; 4 autograph draft; ETON
      Several facsimiles, including P. J. Croft, Autograph Poetry in the English Language, 2 vols, (Oxford, 1969),
      Sherburn (ed.), Elegy (1951)
      , and
      Elegy (1976)
      , where the MS and its provenance are discussed
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 32, 82
      Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), additional lines in the Eton MS, 40-41nn
      Fukuhara/Bergen, Elegy (1933)
      Northup, Bibliography (1917), item 1995
      Munby (ed.), Sale Catalogues (1971), Evans sale (27-29 November 1845), lot 602, 9, Sotheby's sale (28 August 1851), lot 53, 40-41, Sotheby's sale (4 August 1854), lot 226, 69
      W[right]., Catalogue (1851), [lot 53,] 8-9
      Autograph draft, here entitled Stanza's wrote in a Country Church-Yard, and reading "Curfeu". This MS, sometimes called the Eton MS or Fraser MS, contains five additional stanzas (four after l. 72, and the "Redbreast stanza" after l. 116), which were omitted in the first edition of 1751, in 1753, and in 1768.
      MSS 0210, 0211, and 0212.
    - Elegy, written in a Country-Churchyard, 18 December [1750]; mss.0044; poems.elcc; 3 autograph fair copy, faint 227 mm x 188 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 25/11/2006.
      Facsimiles include
      McDermott, Penn and Gray (1930), 14-16
      and
      Fukuhara, Bibliographical Study (1933), plate II
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 33, 82
      Toynbee/Whibley (eds.), Correspondence (1971), letter no. 156, vol. i, 334-340 (subscription required)
      Northup, Bibliography (1917), item 1996
      Catalogue of a Sotheby's sale (27 February 1950), lot 239, facsimile in catalogue
      Autograph fair copy, following a letter to Thomas Wharton, 18 December [1750].
    - Elegy, written in a Country-Church Yard. 1750, mss.0045; poems.elcc; 2 autograph, revised; PBCC
      . Full facsimile published in A facsimile of the original autograph manuscript of Gray's Elegy. Photographed by Messrs. Cundall, Downes & Co. London: Sampson Low, Son, & Co. 1862, other facsimiles include
      Mathias (ed.), Works (1814), vol. I, following p. [64]
      ,
      Poole (ed.), Poetical Works (1917), 90-91
      , and Folger Shakespeare Library, ART Vol. a9, follows p. 50.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 34, 82
      Starr/Hendrickson (eds.), Complete Poems (1966), additional stanza, 42n
      Northup, Bibliography (1917), item 1994
      Autograph, revised, here entitled Elegy, written in a Country-Church Yard. 1750 and reading "Curfeu", with numbered lines (10, 20, etc.), an additional quatrain, the "Redbreast stanza", annotated "Insert" after l. 116 and "Omitted in 1753 ", and an extensive prose note, in Gray's Commonplace Book, vol. II, 617-618.
    - [untitled], [1?] February 1768; mss.0046; poems.elcc; 1 autograph, partial [notes only] 324 mm x 200 mm; BLUK; MS catalogued by Alexander Huber in Manuscripts, British Library, on 04/11/2006.
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 35, 82
      Autograph notes to the poem, untitled but numbered 10. and identified on f. 3r as "10. Elegy, written in a country-churchyard" in MS instructions to Dodsley for the 1768 London edition, sent in a letter, [1?] February 1768. The notes were first published in the poem's version in Poems ( 1768 ).
    - [untitled], 1 February 1768; mss.0047; poems.elcc; [1?] autograph, partial [notes only] 324 mm x 200 mm; PRIN
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), item GrT 36, 82
      Autograph notes to the poem, in MS instructions to Beattie for the 1768 Glasgow edition, originally sent in a letter, 1 February 1768.
    - Stanza written in a Country Church-Yard, [1750?]; mss.0040; poems.elcc; 4 transcript in an unidentified hand; HARV
      Smith (ed.), Index (1989), 82
      Nelson (ed.), Union First Line Index. Mar. 2010. Folger Shakespeare Library. 19 March 2010. <http://firstlines.folger.edu/detail.php?id=36721>
      Transcript in an unidentified hand, entitled Stanza written in a Country Church-Yard, together with a letter from Paget Toynbee suggesting it was a pre-publication transcript that had circulated (lot 46 from an unidentified sale; unknown relationship to Sotheby's sale [ 15 December 1930 ], lot 453, sold to Dobell: 2-page transcript with same title).